The United States and Israel initiated a
major war in the Middle East against
Iran. And the biggest winner of this war
isn't going to be any of them. It's
going to be China instead. Back at the
end of February, when the US and Israel
decided to launch this war, they did so
with the expectation that the exact
opposite outcome would follow with China
becoming severely weakened and humbled.
If the staunchly anti-Western regime in
Iran were toppled by the war, then China
would lose a major source of its
discounted oil. Because of the crippling
financial sanctions placed on Iran by
the West, Iran has always had very few
countries actually willing to purchase
their oil at scale other than China,
which has enabled China to buy up
Iranian oil at a steep discount off of
its usual market value. Roughly 13% of
all of China's oil imports were likely
coming cheaply from Iran immediately
before the war began. And so cutting
that supply off would have placed even
further pressure on China following the
US abduction of Nicholas Maduro in
Venezuela that took place just a few
weeks beforehand.
Similar to Iran, crippling Western
financial sanctions placed on Maduro's
regime in Venezuela had meant that there
were very few countries willing to
purchase Venezuelan oil other than
China, which meant that China could
apply leverage on Venezuela to purchase
their oil for a steep discount. Roughly
3% of China's total oil imports were
similarly coming cheaply from Venezuela,
which the US was able to largely sever
and redirect to itself after they seized
Maduro and changed the country's
leadership through a rapid military
raid. Were the US to manage to topple
the Iranian regime and reroute their oil
exports as well, China would have become
severed from two of its largest sources
of cheap discounted oil, representing
about 16% of its usual total imports
that would have had to have been
replaced from somewhere else. And even
better from Washington's perspective,
China would have become exposed as a
weak bystander of global events that was
unable or unwilling to defend friendly
regimes in both Venezuela and Iran
alike. The US would be able to clearly
display that its superpower strength
still remained the dominant force in
[music] the world, while China would be
shown as a fair weather friend and a
weaker power that could not be relied
upon to help resist Washington. Or so
Washington's theory of victory went when
they decided to start the war. But over
the months since then, all of those
initial American assumptions about how
the war would negatively affect China
have proven to have been disastrously
wrong. The meme of China doing nothing
and winning right now does have some
element of truth behind it. But that
meme betrays the fact that China is
actually doing a lot behind the scenes
to counter whatever America is throwing
[music] at it. It's been well understood
in China for decades now that one of the
country's greatest vulnerabilities is
its lack of oil within their own
borders. China still to this day relies
on imports from abroad to meet about 70%
of its total oil consumption. About half
of which also still comes from around
the Persian Gulf. Thus, if you eliminate
China's oil imports from the Persian
Gulf, you eliminate about 35% of the
source of China's total oil [music]
consumption, which is exactly the
scenario that happened when Iran
enforced a total closure the straight of
Hormos during the war. One would
logically assume that the sudden and
immediate loss of roughly 35% of China's
usual oil supply would have tripled the
Chinese economy. But that didn't
actually ever happen because China has
spent decades diligently preparing for a
scenario that is almost exactly
identical to this. China has always been
very paranoid about what it calls its
Malaa dilemma. The fact that the
overwhelming majority of its critical
oil imports flow through the narrow
straight of Malaa that during wartime
could become easily blockaded by the US
Navy. Defending and countering against
that mala dilemma has been at the core
of Chinese foreign policy for decades
now. But little did Beijing expect that
their preparations for that would also
end up coming in handy for when Iran
shut down the straight of war muz as
well. To prepare for a possible American
blockade of their seaborn oil imports
during a war over Taiwan, China has
pursued a multi-pronged strategy of
diversifying their sources of oil
imports, building up their stockpiles of
oil, and destroying their own domestic
demand for oil. Let's go through these
points one by one. First, China spent
decades quietly building up what has
become the world's largest national
strategic reserve of oil. On paper,
China's strategic reserve of oil might
appear to be lower than America's. By
December of 2025, according to the
Energy Information Administration or
EIA, the Chinese government officially
held 359 million barrels of oil in
reserve, while the US government
officially held 413 million barrels in
reserve. However, most of the commercial
inventories of oil in China that are
technically outside of the official
strategic reserve are also held by
Chinese stateowned oil companies, which
blurs the line between the country's
government- held and commercial held
reserves. While in the US, the country's
commercially held inventories of oil are
fully separate from the government's
reserves. Thus, by the end of 2025, the
Chinese government had effectively
established a strategic reserve of oil
that was more than three times the size
of America's. It was buoied by massive
purchases of oil by the Chinese
throughout 2025 that filled up their
stock piles when the price of oil was
comparatively lower. And it was enough
to fully last 100% of China's usual oil
consumption for more than 100 days
without any additional imports or
societal changes at all. By comparison,
the US strategic reserve only held
enough at the start of 2026 to fully
provide for 100% of America's usual oil
consumption for a mere 20 days, 1/5 as
long as China's. In addition to that,
China's worked hard over the past
several years to radically diversify the
sources of oil they import to reduce
their dependencies on any single given
geographic location. While about half of
China's oil imports come from around the
Persian Gulf through the straight of Arm
Buzz, that ratio was much lower for
China than just about every other nation
in East Asia. Japan relied on about 93%
of its oil imports from the Persian
Gulf. South Korea relied on the region
for about 70% of theirs, while Taiwan
relied on it for about 58% of theirs. So
comparatively to the rest of the major
economies of East Asia, China was
relatively less exposed to disruption in
the straight of Hormuz and they had a
much much larger stockpile of oil held
in reserve to get them through any
crisis as well. And on top of those two
factors, [music] China has also spent
years crafting a national energy
strategy to reduce their economic
dependence on oil as a resource
altogether as well, which ironically has
made heavy use of both coal and
renewable technologies alike. While
China doesn't really have a lot of oil
within their own borders, they do have a
ton of coal. Like to the point where
China has the third largest proven
reserves of coal in the world, just
behind Russia. Thus, China still relies
on its own huge domestic reserves of
coal that can't be blockaded from abroad
to provide for a significant amount of
their own energy and electricity demand.
Roughly 56% of China's total energy
supply still comes from burning coal
compared to only 18% from oil and just
9% from natural gas. And China's
electricity production is even more
lopsided in coal's favor with 60% of the
nation's electricity generated through
coal compared to only 3% from oil and
gas combined. And most of the rest comes
through China's massive investments into
renewable and nuclear energy
technologies.
China installed almost half of the
entire world's solar and wind energy
capacity in 2024. [music]
Solar and wind accounted for 22% of
China's total energy needs in 2022. and
they plan [music] to increase that share
even further to 30% by 2030. At the same
time, China is doubling down on their
nuclear energy as well. In 2024, 4.5% of
China's electricity came from nuclear
power, but they're planning on
increasing that share up to 10% by 2035.
[music] Overall, wind, solar, and
nuclear energy contributed to more than
22% of China's electricity generation in
2024. About another 13% came from
hydropower and another 60% came from
coal. Meaning that China was already
almost completely independent from oil
and gas to keep their electricity going.
By comparison, South Korea still relies
on imported oil and gas to power 29% of
their own electricity. Japan for 34% of
theirs and Taiwan for a whopping 44% of
theirs. In most economies, rising oil
prices most usually affects consumers at
the fuel pump when they go to fill up
their cars with gasoline. But since the
early 2000s, in order to reduce their
dependence on foreign oil even further
and to shield more of their population
from oil supply crunches, China's
pursued a relentless strategy of
adopting as many EVs in the country as
possible. By 2024, roughly 11% of all
the passenger vehicles on the road in
China were EVs. a bit behind countries
like Denmark and Sweden, but well ahead
of any of their regional rivals like
South Korea and the United States with
only a 3% share of EVs on their roads,
or Japan with just a 1% share of EVs on
their roads. All of this combined, from
China's massive stockpiles of oil to its
almost zero use of oil for electricity
generation and to its high adoption rate
of EVs on the road meant that China was
well prepared to weather through a
massive oil supply shock that came when
Iran began blocking the straight of
muzz. China was therefore able to cut
back on their imported oil purchases
during the war by approximately 4
million barrels per day, equivalent to
double the oil consumption rate of
Germany with relatively minimal effects
on their society and economy for several
months.
China cut down on their oil purchases by
so much during the war that it
effectively set a cap on how high the
global price of oil would actually go up
to. Had China not done that, the price
for everyone around the world would have
gotten much, much much worse, and it's
established a lot of leverage over the
United States in doing so. Were China to
begin buying up oil again now at its
usual pace with Hormuz still closed, it
would dramatically jack the price of oil
back up beyond even the highest points
it has reached so far and exacerbate
inflation in the US and everywhere else
in the world too, which the US obviously
doesn't want and which China can use as
leverage right now to gain concessions
out of the US.
All of these strategies were adopted by
China to help the nation get through a
US blockade of their oil imports in the
Balaca Strait. But as it turned out,
they worked just as well to get through
an Iranian blockade of their oil imports
through the straight of Hormuz, too.
Moreover, the way that the war and the
closure of Hormuz spiked global oil
prices has also proven to be a massive
advertisement to other countries for the
great energy technologies that China
currently dominates the manufacturing
of. Governments around the world were
suddenly reminded of how overdependency
on a highly volatile energy resource
like oil can rapidly increase nationwide
inflation when it spikes in price due to
unforeseen events. While demand for
alternative green energy technologies
like solar panels, wind turbines, EVs,
and batteries were already growing even
beforehand anyway. [music] And that
demand has only increased since the war
began. And since the US is the world's
largest oil producer and China is the
world's largest clean energy hardware
producer, this shift is obviously going
to be to China's benefit and America's
detriment. Devoid of hardly any oil
resources in their own territory, China
has been betting big on green energy
alternatives instead for decades. Not
just out of a desire to move away from
fossil fuels for climate reasons, but
also out of raw geopolitical calculus
and energy self-sufficiency.
As early as 2000, China understood that
in order to defeat the western world of
the automotive industry, it needed to
skip over gasoline powered internal
combustion engine vehicles directly to
EVs.
Today, major Chinese EV manufacturing
companies like BYD, Gily, Xpang, and
others control an overwhelming 70% of
the global production of EVs, which also
means that China dominates the global
production of the critical lithium ion
batteries that power EVs as well. 89% of
global lithium-ion battery capacity is
currently manufactured in China [music]
today. And their dominance in green
energy hardware doesn't stop there.
China has similarly bet big on solar
panels since 2000 as well. And today
they produce approximately 80% of the
world's supply of solar panels. Ever
concerned with their own domestic green
energy industries that they want to
protect, both the US and EU have long
maintained high tariffs on Chinese
technology to block their entry into
their markets. The US currently
maintains a steep 100% tariff on Chinese
EVs and a 50% tariff on Chinese solar
panels, while the EU maintains a lower
but still fairly high tariff of 35% on
Chinese EVs as well. But the rest of the
world beyond America and Europe have
been buying [music] up Chinese green
energy tech at record paces since the
war with Iran began. By April, 2 months
after the war against Iran was launched,
China's exports of solar panels were
already up by an astonishing 60%
compared to the year previously. And by
May, their exports of EVs were up by an
even more impressive 110% compared with
the year previously. By attacking Iran
and by being unable to quickly resolve
the Hormos situation, the US and Israel
have effectively done all of the
marketing for China's green energy
technology for them. and have
turbocharged their sales to
never-beforeseen heights in the process.
Then perhaps even more alarmingly for
Washington, the war on Iran is also
increasing a shift in international
currency markets away from the American
dollar and towards the Chinese yuan.
Since the end of the Second World War,
the American dollar has been the
dominant global reserve currency, used
in roughly 80% of international trade
finance. [music]
Historically, this has given the United
States a major advantage when it comes
to policing and controlling trade and
business happening all around the world
because most of the time [music]
international transactions that are
denominated in US dollars have to be
settled by US banks. And since most
international finance transactions are
denominated in US dollars, the US
government has the ability to monitor
most of global trade along with the
ability to cut off or sanction certain
users from access to US dollars and
banks, which cuts them off from access
to most of global trade. This ability
has historically given Washington
enormous power to influence state
behavior all around the world by
threatening and applying sanctions. But
if US adversaries who are sanctioned
begin moving towards an alternative
currency for business like the Chinese
yuan, Washington loses these powers
because the transactions no longer need
to pass through the US banking system.
In 2024 and 2025, roughly 90% of all of
Iran's oil exports were sold to China at
a substantial discount off of the global
market price. And according to the EIA,
most of those transactions were being
settled in Chinese yuan rather than in
US dollars, [music]
which the US can't monitor or sanction.
After Iran shut down the straight of
Hormuz during the war, Iran adopted a
further policy of allowing certain ships
safe [music] passage through so long as
they paid a fee in either yand or
cryptocurrency,
undermining the US-led global financial
order even further. The same thing
started happening after Russia invaded
Ukraine in early 2022.
The US rapidly increased its sanctions
on Russia, blocking them off from the
US-led global finance structure. [music]
And so Russia began denominating more of
their own oil exports and other trade
with China in yuan instead. More than
four years later in mid 2026, the
Russian government says that more than
90% of their trade with China is
dollarfree and is being settled in
either Chinese yuan or Russian rubles
instead. Before the start of the Ukraine
invasion in the torrent of US sanctions,
only 2% of Russian trade transactions
were being denominated in yuan.
According to the center for eastern
studies based in Poland, the primary
global financial messaging network that
most international and crossber payments
are sent through is swift which operates
under EU law which is also heavily
influenced by the United States due to
the global dominance of the dollar. As
such, the US and the EU can cut off
access [music] to Swift to certain
countries which blocks those countries
from being able to operate with most of
the global financial system. Iran,
Russia, and North Korea are all the most
famous examples of countries that have
been largely severed from the Swift
network. But in 2015, China set up its
own separate alternative to the Swift
network that they call the crossber
interbate payment system or [music]
kips, which is also denominated in yuan.
Financial transactions made through kips
cannot be monitored or sanctioned by the
United States. And the volume of
transactions being done on KIPS has been
constantly increasing ever since it was
established. In 2025, the average daily
volume of transactions on KIPS was 680
billion yuan or about $100 billion.
But according to the Atlantic Council, a
think tank based in Washington, over the
three months after the start of the Iran
War, the average daily volume of
transactions on KIPS was $790 billion
yuan or $115 billion,
a 15% increase in transaction volume in
just a single year. Swift still handles
significantly more transactions at more
than $5 trillion per day, but Kips has
already more than quadrupled in its own
transaction volume just since 2020. And
with the rapid growth at sea right now
after the Iran war, it has serious
potential to eventually become a major
competitor or even alternative to Swift.
Over the past 5 years since 2021, the
usage of the yuan in global trade
finance tripled to roughly 6%. And it's
already the second most used global
currency ahead of the euro, but still
behind the dollar. All of this jumping
over to KIPS in the yuan for global
trade and finance which has been growing
even faster since the war on Iran began
means that the US ability to monitor and
sanction global financial flows have
been relatively weakened to China's own
benefit. China has also received an
intangible but still detectable
reputational boost from the American war
on Iran as well. after attacking
Venezuela and seizing their president,
attacking Iran and killing off
significant portions of their leadership
and also threatening Cuba and even
Greenland with similar military actions,
China has been able to present itself to
the world as a more reliable and
predictable steward of the international
order despite its claims to the South
China Sea, Taiwan, and its territorial
disputes with India and Bhutan and
others. These claims all matter, but
they also now seem less reckless to many
than America's recent actions in Iran
have been. By attacking Iran and then by
being unable to force the Straight of
Hormuz back open, the US has angered its
own allies in nearly countless ways.
European allies have been frustrated
with what they view as the unnecessary
rise in oil prices and inflation caused
by the war. Along with Trump's demands
that they militarily assist against Iran
for a war they neither started nor
wanted. G state allies have been
frustrated by the damage that has been
dealt to their cities, infrastructure
and economies that is pushing some of
them like Saudi Arabia and Qatar to
rebalance between both the US and China
alike. And East Asian allies have been
frustrated by Washington showing yet
again that they are simply not America's
top foreign policy priority. For the
first time ever, the US military
redeployed critical Patrian missile
batteries and fed interceptors from
South Korea to the Middle East. as the
war on Iran dragged on for longer than
expected. While they also redeployed the
USS Abraham Lincoln aircraft carrier
from the South China [music] Sea to the
Middle East as well, exposing South
Korea more to North Korea and reducing
US military assets in East Asia around
China, tipping the military balance in
the region towards China's favor. These
emerging points of divergence between
the US and its allies over the Iran war
will be able to be exploited
diplomatically by China. But perhaps no
other US ally will be as rattled by the
war on Iran as Taiwan. Taiwanese
leadership, which has long assumed that
the US military would likely come to its
aid in the event of a crossstraight
Chinese invasion, is now being forced to
watch what's happening in Iran with
tremendous anxiety. The US is blowing
through tens of billions of dollars
worth of munitions in Iran that could
have been stockpiled for a future war in
East Asia. But they also now have to ask
a rather uncomfortable question. If the
US military can't even defeat a second
rate regional military power like Iran
right now, then would the US really risk
a much much larger war with China over
the defense of Taiwan? China would
always prefer to compel Taiwan into
reunifying with the mainland through
diplomacy and leverage rather than
through an unpredictable and potentially
costly war. China's strategy here has
always been to appear to make it seem
inevitable no matter what ends up
happening. America's floundering war in
Iran will enable Chinese propaganda to
portray America as a spent, exhausted
force that'll be unable or unwilling to
resist a [music] Chinese takeover of
Taiwan, which might be able to pressure
Taiwan's leadership into becoming more
amendable to the idea of cooperation
with China. nearly all around the world.
The global opinion between China and the
United States has also been shifting in
China's favor since the Iran War began,
too. The Pew Research Center, another
think tank based in Washington, has been
tracking the global sentiment between
China and the United States every year
since 2002 through polling. And
recently, between February and May of
2026, Pew pulled more than 42,000 people
across 36 countries on this same issue.
And for the first time since they began
tracking in 2002, they found that 25 out
of those 36 countries held a more
favorable view of China, including
[music] within several ostensibly US
allies like Germany, Argentina,
Australia, the Netherlands, France,
Canada, Greece, Italy, Spain, Turkey,
and Thailand. Compared to the year
previously in 2025, Canada, Greece,
Spain, Italy, and Indonesia all saw the
biggest opinion shifts away from America
and towards China. While positive views
of China reached all-time highs in many
countries like Italy, Spain, Turkey,
Mexico, and Colombia. Notably, out of
all of the countries in Europe who were
surveyed in 2026 after the Iran war had
started, only two of them continue to
hold more favorable views of the US than
China. Poland and Hungary. Every single
other country in both Western and
Southern Europe who were surveyed now
hold higher opinions of China instead
with the strongest percentages in
China's favor now being seen in Spain,
Italy, Greece, and Turkey. America and
Israel's war on Iran hasn't been
entirely positive for China. China has
still been negatively affected by rising
energy prices, lagging global demand,
and disrupted supply chains that have
all negatively affected its
manufacturingbased economy. But when
compared to the negatives that the
United States has experienced, China is
unquestionably coming out of this
conflict ahead, and it's had to do
basically nothing in order to achieve
that. Over the past quarter of a
century, the US has now expended itself
in three massive and strategically
dubious military adventures in the
Middle East region against Afghanistan,
against Iraq, and now against Iran. All
the while, China has been patiently
improving in conserving its
manufacturing and military strengths and
diplomatic leverage. Napoleon Bonapart
when he was emperor of the French once
famously said to never interrupt your
enemy while he is making a mistake. And
for China and Xiinping today, that maxim
has never sounded more clear than it
does today.
And if you want to learn more about
Xiinping, like where he came from, what
he believes in, and how his leadership
is radically changing China today, I
know exactly what you should go and
watch next right now. or at least put on
your list. And that's the China that she
grew up in, a grand theory of Xihinp, a
documentary series at the Nebula
exclusive, which means that it exists
only on the streaming service that
myself and a whole bunch of other
creators put together called Nebula.
Created by my friend Polyatter, this
documentary series explores the dramatic
rise to power of Xihinping in China.
From sleeping on the floor of a cave to
leading one of the two global
superpowers of the 21st century, it's an
incredible story that is well worth your
time and will help you understand even
more about the modern world we live in.
Then there were also my own projects on
Nebula like Mad Kees, a show that
explores the darker histories of some of
modern history's most well-known
dictators, including other recent
historical figures who have clashed with
the Western world like Libya's Muamar
Gaddafi and Iraq's U Hussein, along with
episodes covering the reigns of North
Korea's Kim Sunung and Kim Jong-il that
explore how they were actually able to
avoid a US intervention. And then
there's also my other Nebula series
called Modern Conflicts, which explores
modern wars, battles, and conflicts in a
level of depth and detail that would
never [music] work out on YouTube
without triggering this site's
demonetization and age restriction
policies with episodes you can watch
covering the Israel Palestinian
conflict, Hamas's attack on Israel on
October 7th, the overthrow of the Assad
[music] regime in Syria, Israel's
invasion of the Gaza Strip, and the
Russia Ukraine war that explain the
crucial backstory information you need
to understand what's currently happening
across major geopolitical conflicts
happening all around the world right
now. These are my own projects, but
there's also just so much good stuff on
Nebula from other creators right now
that you can go and watch, too. There's
Day Pass, hosted by Jason from Not Just
Bikes, that explores the world through
the lens of public transportation down
on the ground. If you ever wondered what
happened to Lindsay Ellis, she's been
making her usual video essays on Nebula
for years now instead of on YouTube.
There's Patrick Williams' latest short
film, The Dinner Plan, featuring big
names like Griffin Newman and Zack
Cherry. There's Abolish Everything, our
new comedy debate premise recorded live
in [music] New York. Scav, a docky
series produced by the one of her
productions in Jetlag folks [music]
tracing the incredible drama and hij
jinks of the world's largest annual
scavenger hunt hosted by the University
of Chicago and oldest and newest places
by Joe Scott. A fulllength documentary
exploring the oldest and newest rocks on
the planet and what it takes to actually
visit them. I can honestly just keep
going and going, but just believe me
when I say that with every month that
goes by, the Nebula catalog keeps
getting deeper, making becoming a
subscriber even better. But we also need
you to help keep this whole cycle going.
We also have a great deal running right
now that when you use my link at
nebula.tv/realifelorore TV/realife
or by scanning the QR code on your
screen or clicking the button, you'll
get a whole 50% off of an annual Nebula
subscription, which will bring the cost
for you down to just $30 for the entire
year or 250 per month, a small fraction
of the price of other streaming
services. As other streamers keep
raising their prices, this is an awesome
deal. And if you want to sign up for a
lifetime subscription to Nebula and then
never have to deal with a monthly
subscription ever again, you can get one
for 40% off right now for $300 as well.
So go ahead and give us a shot. And
thank you so much for supporting not
only my own channel, but all of the
other creators who are helping to build
Nebula with their own awesome, unique
content as well. And as always, thank
[music] you so much for watching.